<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <Case-Studies>   <Case-Study name="Forest Macrogroups of the Americas: '1.B.2.Na.16 - South-Central Oak - Hardwood and Pine Forest'" id="FerrerParis_Continental_ForestMacrogroup_2017_42">     <Case-Study-Names>       <Case-Study-Name lang="en">Forest Macrogroups of the Americas: '1.B.2.Na.16 - South-Central Oak - Hardwood and Pine Forest'</Case-Study-Name>     </Case-Study-Names>     <Scope>       <Scope-descriptions>         <Scope-description lang="en">The risk assessment covered the entire distribution of the assessment target as described by the classification scheme and distribution maps available.</Scope-description>       </Scope-descriptions>       <Scope-classification id="IUCN Scope" version="1.0" selected="no" assigned-by="JRFEP">         <Scope-classification-element level="1">1. Global</Scope-classification-element>       </Scope-classification>     </Scope>     <Assessment-type>Systematic</Assessment-type>     <Assessment-Information date="2020-04-30" reviewer="Rsaurio" status="auto-generated-test" load="false">       <ref-label>FerrerParis_Continental_ForestMacrogroup_2017</ref-label>       <Assessment-date>2018-10-15</Assessment-date>       <Assessment-authors>         <Author>JR Ferrer-Paris</Author>         <Author>I Zager</Author>       </Assessment-authors>       <Assessment-collaborators>         <Collaborator>C. Josse</Collaborator>         <Collaborator>M. A. Oliveira‐Miranda</Collaborator>         <Collaborator>M. González‐Gil</Collaborator>         <Collaborator>D. Velarde</Collaborator>         <Collaborator>G. C. De La Cruz-Melo</Collaborator>         <Collaborator>E. Primiciero</Collaborator>       </Assessment-collaborators>       <Assessment-reviewers>         <Reviewer/>       </Assessment-reviewers>       <Assessment-Keywords>         <Keyword>Woodlands</Keyword>         <Keyword>Climate change</Keyword>         <Keyword>Defaunation</Keyword>         <Keyword>Anthromes</Keyword>         <Keyword>Surface water</Keyword>       </Assessment-Keywords>     </Assessment-Information>     <Assessment-Target date="2020-04-30" updated-by="Rsaurio" status="auto-generated-test">       <AT-id>STME_Montane_Humid_Forest_42</AT-id>       <AT-descriptions>         <AT-description lang="en">The '1.B.2.Na.16 - South-Central Oak - Hardwood and Pine Forest' is a forest macrogroup belonging to the '1.B.2.Na Eastern North American and Great Plains Cool Temperate Forest and Woodland' division in the International Vegetation Classification system (Faber-Langendoen et al. 2014). It is considered here as a proxy for a forest ecosystem type in a regional assessment of forest ecosystems in the Americas.</AT-description>       </AT-descriptions>       <AT-names>         <AT-name lang="en">1.B.2.Na.16 - South-Central Oak - Hardwood and Pine Forest</AT-name>       </AT-names>       <Characteristic-biota>         <Biota-Summaries>           <Biota-Summary lang="en">A list of 62 characteristic species was extracted from descriptive profiles of the Macrogroup and related ecological systems.</Biota-Summary>         </Biota-Summaries>         <taxons>           <taxon>Quercus</taxon>           <taxon>Pinus</taxon>           <taxon>Pinus palustris</taxon>           <taxon>Quercus Spp.</taxon>           <taxon>Quercus alba</taxon>           <taxon>Quercus coccinea</taxon>           <taxon>Quercus falcata</taxon>           <taxon>Quercus rubra</taxon>           <taxon>Quercus stellata</taxon>           <taxon>Quercus velutina</taxon>           <taxon>Carya alba</taxon>           <taxon>Carya glabra</taxon>           <taxon>Carya ovata</taxon>           <taxon>Carya pallida</taxon>           <taxon>Carya Spp.</taxon>           <taxon>Quercus prinus</taxon>           <taxon>Pinus echinata</taxon>           <taxon>Pinus taeda</taxon>           <taxon>Pinus virginiana</taxon>           <taxon>Acer rubrum</taxon>           <taxon>Liquidambar styraciflua</taxon>           <taxon>Liriodendron tulipifera</taxon>           <taxon>Nyssa sylvatica</taxon>           <taxon>Quercus marilandica</taxon>           <taxon>Carya texana</taxon>           <taxon>Fraxinus quadrangulata</taxon>           <taxon>Juniperus virginiana</taxon>           <taxon>Quercus muehlenbergii</taxon>           <taxon>Quercus pagoda</taxon>           <taxon>Quercus shumardii</taxon>           <taxon>Vaccinium pallidum</taxon>           <taxon>Callicarpa americana</taxon>           <taxon>Rhododendron minus</taxon>           <taxon>Kalmia latifolia</taxon>           <taxon>Solidago odora</taxon>           <taxon>Euphorbia corollata</taxon>           <taxon>Piptochaetium avenaceum</taxon>           <taxon>Ulmus alata</taxon>           <taxon>Quercus incana</taxon>           <taxon>Danthonia spicata</taxon>           <taxon>Sorghastrum nutans</taxon>           <taxon>Dichanthelium commutatum (= Panicum commutatum)</taxon>           <taxon>Sassafras albidum</taxon>           <taxon>Quercus arkansana</taxon>           <taxon>Ilex vomitoria</taxon>           <taxon>Panicum virgatum</taxon>           <taxon>Gaylussacia baccata</taxon>           <taxon>Schizachyrium scoparium</taxon>           <taxon>Vaccinium arboreum</taxon>           <taxon>Chasmanthium laxum</taxon>           <taxon>Prosopis glandulosa</taxon>           <taxon>Pityopsis graminifolia</taxon>           <taxon>Tephrosia virginiana</taxon>           <taxon>Helianthus microcephalus</taxon>           <taxon>Fraxinus americana</taxon>           <taxon>Andropogon Spp.</taxon>           <taxon>Pteridium aquilinum</taxon>           <taxon>Pinus rigida</taxon>           <taxon>Andropogon gerardii</taxon>           <taxon>Coreopsis major</taxon>           <taxon>Cornus florida</taxon>           <taxon>Juniperus virginiana var. virginiana</taxon>         </taxons>       </Characteristic-biota>       <Abiotic-environment>         <Abiotic-Summaries>           <Abiotic-Summary lang="en">Information on soil and general climatic conditions was extracted from descriptive profiles of the Macrogroup and related ecological systems.</Abiotic-Summary>           <Abiotic-Summary lang="es">. Las precipitaciones oscila entre unos 120 cm en la parte noreste y alrededor de 70 cm en el suroeste, donde se convierte en cada vez más errático. Los sustratos varían ampliamente, incluye suelos derivados de rocas metamórficas félsicas y máficas; calizas sedimentarias, areniscas, y lutitas; así como algunas llanuras costeras de poco sedimentos de limos y arcillas. Estos suelos van desde calcárea a ácido; suelos pueden ser muy poco profundo a excesivamente bien drenados .Ejemplos también pueden ocurrir en capas duras de arcilla densa sobre rocas máficas. . Los depósitos aluviales del Pleistoceno suelen ser de arena, y en una zona muy limitada, hay afloramientos de piedra arenisca de origen incierto. Los suelos incluidos en este sistema, en el oeste de Tennessee son ricos, productiva y limosa, que se deriva de los depósitos de loess relativamente gruesas. . Los suelos de este sistema son generalmente Alfisoles, son típicamente ácido a neutro, y van desde superficiales a moderadamente profundo.. suelos de piedra arenisca. Suelos de arenisca y pedernal. El sustrato es típicamente roca ígnea o metamórfica máficas (gabro, basalto, diabasa, o amphibolite), pero en ocasiones es pizarra. Sustratos geológicos varían. La mayoría de las porciones son secas, pero existen zonas húmedas ocasionales . Suelos acidos. Los suelos son generalmente ácido, aunque pueden aparacer en los suelos calcáreos. Los suelos son arcilloso a arcillosos y bien drenados, pero no excesivamente drenado.. Este sistema se puede producir en cualquier tipo de roca,  la química de la roca es un determinante importante de variación. Los suelos son casi toda la gama de los suelos de las tierras altas, con sólo los suelos rocosos someros y aquellos con capas duras de arcillas.</Abiotic-Summary>         </Abiotic-Summaries>       </Abiotic-environment>       <Biotic-processes>         <Processes-Summaries>           <Processes-Summary lang="en">Information on biotic characteristics and processes was extracted from descriptive profiles of the Macrogroup and related ecological systems.</Processes-Summary>           <Processes-Summary lang="es">Estos bosques de roble-pino y roble-madera, dependientes del fuego, se encuentran en una banda ancha en todo el sureste de Estados Unido. Maderas típicas incluyen  Quercus alba, Quercus coccinea, Quercus falcata, Quercus rubra, Quercus stellata , Quercus velutina  pallida  y Pinos incluyen Pinus echinata, Pinus taeda  y Pinus virginiana.. Laderas y barrancos están dominados por bosques frondosos mésicos o seco-mésicos tales como los de la arista sur, pero son de alcance relativamente limitado. Estos bosques se producen en las crestas de arena en un entorno diseccionado.. Este sistema contiene robles y otras maderas duras. Algunos dominantes típicas incluyen canopy falcata Quercus, Quercus alba, Carya alba, Quercus stellata, Quercus marilandica, y Quercus velutina. La extensión del área de este sistema forestal ha sido tan fuertemente reducida.  Se produce generalmente en suelos arenosos o arcillosos, es diseccionado por drenajes. Se distingue de la pradera cercana por la mayor densidad de árboles y la diversidad de especies leñosas. Estos bosques se producen en las cumbres estrechas y pendientes en un entorno altamente disecados. bosques mantenidos por el fuego. Los Bosques en las crestas de las colinas están dominadas por Quercus alba, Quercus rubra, Quercus falcata, Quercus pagoda, Quercus stellata, Carya texana, Quercus shumardii, y Quercus velutina.. Este sistema se limita principalmente a suavemente inclinado moderadamente, planicies de tierras altas. El sistema se desarrolla mejor en grandes porciones del paisaje que son planas a suavemente ondulada y que llevaría bien el fuego, creando un extenso sector de incendio naturales. La región comtiene  bosques de dosel cerrado.  En algunos ejemplos de este sistema, la importancia de las maderas duras como el roble puede ser mayor que el pino, especialmente en sitios subxericos y mésicos.. ESte sistema del sur de Piamonte se produce en lugares donde hay una densa capa dura de arcillay se ha desarrollado a lo largo de una gama de rocas máficas normalmente. En las partes más profundas del suelo de este sistema, la densidad de la arcilla, en combinación con sus propiedades de contracción, limita el agua y penetración de las raíces en el suelo y crea condiciones para plantas xerófilas a pesar de la presencia de suelos profundos.. Este sistema abarca los bosques de llanura no costeras mantenidos por el fuego y los bosques donde Pinus palustris es una especie de dosel dominantes o codominantes. Son naturalmente, bosques abiertos pero existen  bosques de arbustos densos o con poca cobertura del suelo. sistema puede estar limitado a sustratos ácidos. El fuego es, sin duda, una influencia muy importante y necesario.  Los robles son medianamente comun. El estrato arbustivo puede ser bien desarrollado, con baccata Gaylussacia, latifolia Kalmia u otras especies tolerantes a ácido más característico.. Este sistema abarca bosques de robles, lugares donde se produce este sistema son un tanto protegidos de la mayoría de los incendios naturales por alguna combinación de topografía empinada, el aislamiento de la propagación del fuego, y la inflamabilidad limitado de la vegetación. . Estos bosques, probablemente, existían como bosques primarios.. Este sistema abarca los bosques de tierras altas predominantes del sur de Piamonte, están dominadas normalmente por combinaciones de robles de tierras altas, a veces con pinos como un componente significativo, sobre todo en la parte sur de la región. Estos bosques se presentan en una variedad de hábitats y, en condiciones naturales, es el tipo de vegetación que cubre la mayor parte de la matriz del paisaje.</Processes-Summary>         </Processes-Summaries>       </Biotic-processes>       <Ecosystem-services>         <Services>           <Ecosystem-service/>         </Services>         <Services-Summaries>           <Services-Summary lang="en"/>         </Services-Summaries>       </Ecosystem-services>       <Threats>         <Threats-Summaries>           <Threats-Summary lang="en"></Threats-Summary>         </Threats-Summaries>         <Threat>           <Threat-name>Increase in human population density</Threat-name>           <Threat-description lang="en">Increasing human population can be a cause of loss of woodland distribution due to increase in resource use, expansion of infrastructure, and changes in land use. It is also indirectly associated to the spread of invasive species.</Threat-description>           <Threat-Impact>             <Threat-Timing id="IUCN" version="3.2" selected="yes" assigned-by="JRFP">Ongoing</Threat-Timing>             <Threat-Scope id="IUCN" version="3.2" selected="yes" assigned-by="JRFP">Unknown</Threat-Scope>             <Threat-Severity id="IUCN" version="3.2" selected="yes" assigned-by="JRFP">Unknown</Threat-Severity>           </Threat-Impact>           <Threat-classification id="IUCN" version="3.2" selected="yes" assigned-by="JRFP">             <Threat-classification-element level="1">1 Residential and commercial development</Threat-classification-element>             <Threat-classification-element level="1">4 Transportation and service corridors</Threat-classification-element>             <Threat-classification-element level="1">6 Human intrusions and disturbance</Threat-classification-element>           </Threat-classification>         </Threat>         <Threat>           <Threat-name>Higher intensity of agriculture</Threat-name>           <Threat-description lang="en">NA</Threat-description>           <Threat-Impact>             <Threat-Timing id="IUCN" version="3.2" selected="yes" assigned-by="JRFP">Ongoing</Threat-Timing>             <Threat-Scope id="IUCN" version="3.2" selected="yes" assigned-by="JRFP">Unknown</Threat-Scope>             <Threat-Severity id="IUCN" version="3.2" selected="yes" assigned-by="JRFP">Unknown</Threat-Severity>           </Threat-Impact>           <Threat-classification id="IUCN" version="3.2" selected="yes" assigned-by="JRFP">             <Threat-classification-element level="1">2 Agriculture and aquaculture</Threat-classification-element>             <Threat-classification-element level="2">2.1 Annual and perennial non-timber crops</Threat-classification-element>             <Threat-classification-element level="2">2.2 Wood and pulp plantations</Threat-classification-element>           </Threat-classification>         </Threat>         <Threat>           <Threat-name>Expansion of grazing stock</Threat-name>           <Threat-description lang="en">NA</Threat-description>           <Threat-Impact>             <Threat-Timing id="IUCN" version="3.2" selected="yes" assigned-by="JRFP">Ongoing</Threat-Timing>             <Threat-Scope id="IUCN" version="3.2" selected="yes" assigned-by="JRFP">Unknown</Threat-Scope>             <Threat-Severity id="IUCN" version="3.2" selected="yes" assigned-by="JRFP">Unknown</Threat-Severity>           </Threat-Impact>           <Threat-classification id="IUCN" version="3.2" selected="yes" assigned-by="JRFP">             <Threat-classification-element level="1">2 Agriculture and aquaculture</Threat-classification-element>             <Threat-classification-element level="2">2.3 Livestock farming and ranching</Threat-classification-element>           </Threat-classification>         </Threat>         <Threat>           <Threat-name>Deforestation</Threat-name>           <Threat-description lang="en">Elimination of tree cover.</Threat-description>           <Threat-Impact>             <Threat-Timing id="IUCN" version="3.2" selected="yes" assigned-by="JRFP">Ongoing</Threat-Timing>             <Threat-Scope id="IUCN" version="3.2" selected="yes" assigned-by="JRFP">Unknown</Threat-Scope>             <Threat-Severity id="IUCN" version="3.2" selected="yes" assigned-by="JRFP">Unknown</Threat-Severity>           </Threat-Impact>           <Threat-classification id="IUCN" version="3.2" selected="yes" assigned-by="JRFP">             <Threat-classification-element level="1">5 Biological resource use</Threat-classification-element>             <Threat-classification-element level="2">5.3 Logging and wood harvesting</Threat-classification-element>           </Threat-classification>         </Threat>         <Threat>           <Threat-name>Climate change</Threat-name>           <Threat-description lang="en">Climate conditions are generally considered of great importance for the maintainance of forest vegetation and characteristic processes of several macrogroups, and were also incorporated in the process of macrogroup potential distribution modeling and validation (Bow et al. 2008; Josse et al. 2009)⁠. Thus we considered climate change as a plausible future threat of degradation of environmental conditions (Laurance and Williamson 2001; Tovar et al. 2013)</Threat-description>           <Threat-Impact>             <Threat-Timing id="IUCN" version="3.2" selected="yes" assigned-by="JRFP">Only in the future</Threat-Timing>             <Threat-Scope id="IUCN" version="3.2" selected="yes" assigned-by="JRFP">Unknown</Threat-Scope>             <Threat-Severity id="IUCN" version="3.2" selected="yes" assigned-by="JRFP">Unknown</Threat-Severity>           </Threat-Impact>           <Threat-classification id="IUCN" version="3.2" selected="yes" assigned-by="JRFP">             <Threat-classification-element level="1">11 Climate change and severe weather</Threat-classification-element>             <Threat-classification-element level="2">11.1 Habitat shifting and alteration</Threat-classification-element>           </Threat-classification>         </Threat>         <Threat>           <Threat-name>Defaunation</Threat-name>           <Threat-description lang="en">Defaunation is considered a large and pervasive threat to biodiversity, the loss of large vertebrates due to overexploitation has an impact in important biotic associations in ecosystems (Galetti and Dirzo 2013; Dirzo et al. 2014)⁠.</Threat-description>           <Threat-Impact>             <Threat-Timing id="IUCN" version="3.2" selected="yes" assigned-by="JRFP">Ongoing</Threat-Timing>             <Threat-Scope id="IUCN" version="3.2" selected="yes" assigned-by="JRFP">Unknown</Threat-Scope>             <Threat-Severity id="IUCN" version="3.2" selected="yes" assigned-by="JRFP">Unknown</Threat-Severity>           </Threat-Impact>           <Threat-classification id="IUCN" version="3.2" selected="yes" assigned-by="JRFP">             <Threat-classification-element level="1">5 Biological resource use</Threat-classification-element>             <Threat-classification-element level="2">5.1 Hunting and collecting terrestrial animals</Threat-classification-element>             <Threat-classification-element level="3">5.1.4 Motivation Unknown/Unrecorded</Threat-classification-element>           </Threat-classification>         </Threat>       </Threats>       <Conservation-actions>         <Conservation-Summaries>           <Conservation-Summary lang="en"/>         </Conservation-Summaries>         <Conservation-action>           <Conservation-action-names>             <Conservation-action-name lang="en"/>           </Conservation-action-names>           <Conservation-action-descriptions>             <Conservation-action-description lang="en"/>           </Conservation-action-descriptions>           <Conservation-action-classification id="" version="0" selected="" assigned-by="">             <Conservation-action-classification-element level="none"/>           </Conservation-action-classification>         </Conservation-action>       </Conservation-actions>       <Research-needs>         <Research-Summaries>           <Research-Summary lang="en"/>         </Research-Summaries>         <Research-needed>           <Research-needed-names>             <Research-needed-name lang="en"/>           </Research-needed-names>           <Research-needed-descriptions>             <Research-needed-description lang="en"/>           </Research-needed-descriptions>           <Research-needed-classification id="" version="0" selected="" assigned-by="">             <Research-needed-classification-element level="none"/>           </Research-needed-classification>         </Research-needed>       </Research-needs>       <Conceptual-ecosystem-model>         <CEM-summaries>           <CEM-summary lang="en">A general conceptual model is presented graphically in Fig. S1. We include in this model the most important large scale threats to forest in the Americas: loss of forest cover due to agriculture and live stock expansion; defaunation due to hunting (or 'empty forest syndrome'), structural and compositional changes due to selective logging and invasion of exotic species, changes in disturbance regimes due to land use practices and development and shifting climatic conditions due to climate change.</CEM-summary>         </CEM-summaries>         <CEM-type graphic="yes">Cause-effect</CEM-type>         <CEM-source>Assessment authors, based on Laurance and Williamson (2001), Allen et al. (2010), Faber-Langendoen et al. (2014), Lewis et al. (2015), Levis et al. (2017)</CEM-source>       </Conceptual-ecosystem-model>       <Classifications>         <Classification-system id="IUCN habitat" version="3.0" selected="yes" assigned-by="Assessment authors">           <Classification-element level="1">1. Forest</Classification-element>           <Classification-element level="2">1.4. Forest – Temperate</Classification-element>         </Classification-system>         <Classification-system id="RLE Global Typology" version="draft" selected="no" assigned-by="Assessment authors">           <Classification-element level="1">Terrestrial</Classification-element>           <Classification-element level="2">T2 Temperate-boreal forests and woodlands</Classification-element>           <Classification-element level="3">T2.1 Boreal and montane needle-leaved forest and woodland</Classification-element>         </Classification-system>         <Classification-system id="IVC" version="2014" selected="no" assigned-by="Assessment authors">           <Classification-element level="1">1 Forest and Woodland</Classification-element>           <Classification-element level="2">1.B Temperate and Boreal Forest and Woodland</Classification-element>           <Classification-element level="3">1.B.2 Cool Temperate Forest and Woodland</Classification-element>           <Classification-element level="4">1.B.2.Na Eastern North American and Great Plains Cool Temperate Forest and Woodland</Classification-element>           <Classification-element level="5">1.B.2.Na.16 - South-Central Oak - Hardwood and Pine Forest</Classification-element>         </Classification-system>       </Classifications>       <Distribution>         <Distribution-Summaries>           <Distribution-Summary lang="es">Esta vegetación se encuentra en la mayor parte del sudeste de los Estados Unidos, en las llanuras costeras y las regiones interiores adyacentes, desde el Piedemonte y Atlántico adyacente al  llano costero de Maryland y Alabama; las elevaciones más bajas de los Apalaches, hacia el oeste a través del Interior Baja Meseta (con límite norte en el extremo sureste de Ohio, el sur de Indiana y el sur de Illinois), los Ozarks y Ouachitas de Arkansas, Missouri, el sureste de Kansas, Oklahoma, y hacia el sur en Virginia , las Carolinas y la llanura costera del Golfo Este desde Georgia a Mississippi, la llanura costera del Golfo Occidental y la llanura costera de Tejas interior. Este sistema es endémica en  Crowley's Ridge en el río Mississippi Y en llanura aluvial de Arkansas y Missouri Este sistema habría ocupado las partes más septentrionales del Alto Golfo Oriente, llanura costera del oeste de Tennessee, Kentucky occidental, posiblemente el sur de Illinois y el norte de Mississippi. Este sistema ecológico se encuentra en el centro-este de Texas en una amplia, banda noreste / suroeste situado al oeste del Golfo, al noroeste de la pradera costera, y al este y al sur de las ecorregiones Blackland Prairie. Un brazo se extiende a lo largo del río Rojo en el norte de Texas. Este sistema es endémica de sitios bien drenados sobre Crowley's Ridge  (Arkansas, Missouri) y Louisiana,  a lo largo de la vertiente oriental de la terraza Grand Prairie en Arkansas, y tal vez otros sitios en el río Mississippi, incluyendo Missouri y extremo occidental de Kentucky y Tennessee. Este sistema se produce en la región de Ouachita y Ozark montañas de Arkansas, Oklahoma, y el sur de Missouri. Este sistema se produce en la región de Ouachita y Ozark montañas de Arkansas, Oklahoma y el sur de Missouri. Piedemonte de Maryland, Virginia, Carolina del Norte, Carolina del Sur y Georgia. Partes del Piamonte sobre todo exterior, desde el centro de Carolina del Norte a Alabama,  en el noreste de Alabama y el noroeste de Georgia. Áreas más extensas están ahora en gran parte, si no exclusivamente, restringidos a la zona centro-sur de Carolina del Norte (Piamonte exterior) y Alabama oriental, así como el Valle de Alabama. Restos más pequeños se encuentran en áreas muy limitadas de Carolina del Sur y Georgia (como Pine Mountain). Bosques de robles secos como falcata Quercus, Quercus prinus, y Quercus coccinea,  Carya glabra, Acer rubrum, y otros. El estrato arbustivo puede ser bien desarrollado. Las hierbas son generalmente escasos pero pueden incluir Pityopsis graminifolia y Tephrosia virginiana. Este sistema abarca desde el sureste de Virginia (sur del río James) hacia el sur hasta el sureste de Georgia en la llanura costera del Atlántico. Este sistema se extiende a lo largo del Piamonte desde Alabama a Virginia. En Virginia, es sobre todo el centro y sur, sino que se extiende en una porción estrecha del norte de Virginia en la eco-región de Piamonte.</Distribution-Summary>         </Distribution-Summaries>         <Biogeographic-realms>           <Biogeographic-realm>Nearctic</Biogeographic-realm>         </Biogeographic-realms>         <Spatial-data/>       </Distribution>       <Collapse-definition>         <Collapse-summaries>           <Collapse-summary lang="en"/>         </Collapse-summaries>         <Spatial-collapse-definitions>           <Spatial-collapse lang="en">As the tree growth form is the main structural element of any forest macrogroup, a forest macrogroup was assumed to collapse if the original woodland cover was completely replaced by a non-woodland cover, or if the tree-cover within its potential distribution declined to zero (criteria A and B).</Spatial-collapse>         </Spatial-collapse-definitions>         <Functional-collapse-definitions>           <Functional-collapse lang="en">For assessing environmental degradation under criterion C, we considered two different indicators. In the case of climate change, we assume that the ecosystem collapsed if the climatic conditions shifted from mostly suitable for the focus macrogroup, to mostly suitable to a different macrogroup. Additionally for flooded and swamp forest, we assumed ecosystem collapse if the amount of detected surface water within the potential distribution of the macrogroup declined to zero.  For assessing disruption to biotic processes and interactions under criterion D we assumed that most of the fundamental processes and interactions disappeared with intensive use of woodlands under high population density. We also assumed that the ecosystem would collapse if the population of large mammals declined to less than 10% of their original population size.</Functional-collapse>         </Functional-collapse-definitions>       </Collapse-definition>     </Assessment-Target>     <Ecosystem-Risk-Assessment date="2020-04-30" updated-by="Rsaurio" status="auto-generated-test">       <Assessment-version>2.2</Assessment-version>       <Risk-assessment-protocol>IUCN RLE</Risk-assessment-protocol>       <Assessment-unit>         <Ecosystem-subset>           <Subset-descriptions>             <Subset-description lang="en">This assessment refers to the entire distribution of the assessment target as delimited by the assessment authors.</Subset-description>           </Subset-descriptions>           <Countries>             <Country iso-code-2="US">United States</Country>           </Countries>           <Spatial-data>             <Spatial-point datum="WGS84" proj="longlat" type="lower-left-corner">               <x>-99.9182059827072</x>               <y>26.8599491020766</y>               <radius units="degrees">0.0001</radius>             </Spatial-point>             <Spatial-point datum="WGS84" proj="longlat" type="upper-right-corner">               <x>-74.1227616344116</x>               <y>40.772343822214</y>               <radius units="degrees">0.0001</radius>             </Spatial-point>           </Spatial-data>         </Ecosystem-subset>         <RA-Summaries>           <RA-Summary lang="en">The IUCN Red List of Ecosystem assessment of the Macrogroup '1.B.2.Na.16 - South-Central Oak - Hardwood and Pine Forest' was based on 5 indicators evaluated over different time frames: past and historic decline in woodland cover, current extent and trends in tree cover, predicted future changes in climatic suitability, past and historic changes in the intensity of land use, potential defaunation of medium and large mammals. It was estimated that, at the present rate of decline in tree cover, the geographic distribution could decline 59.2 % in a 50-year period; thus, the ecosystem is classified as Endangered under sub-criterion A2b. Uncertainty in this estimate (90% C.I. 44.2 -- 70.2 %) suggests a plausible range from Vulnerable to Endangered. It was estimated that the geographic distribution measured as woodland cover declined 73 % historically; thus, the ecosystem is classified as Endangered under sub-criterion A3. Uncertainty in this estimate (90% C.I. 61.1 -- 81.2 %) suggests a plausible range from Vulnerable to Endangered. Thus the overall category is Endangered with plausible bounds Vulnerable to Endangered.</RA-Summary>         </RA-Summaries>         <Rationale/>         <Overall-category>EN</Overall-category>         <Plausible-bounds lower="VU" upper="EN"/>         <Supporting-subcriteria>A2b+A3</Supporting-subcriteria>         <Criterions>           <Criterion name="A">             <Summaries>               <Summary lang="en">For this macrogroup, forest vegetation is the dominant and diagnostic growth form. Thus, we consider presence of trees (as closed forest or woodlands) as a characteristic element and the main indicator of spatial distribution of the macrogroups. In order to cover both historical and present changes in distribution, we selected two different data sources that estimate tree presence: “woodlands” cover from historic biome and land use reconstruction (subcriteria A1 and A3), and percentage tree cover calculated from a combination of contemporary remote sensing data (subcriterion A2b)⁠.</Summary>             </Summaries>             <Rationales>               <Rationale lang="en">Subcriterion A2bandA3 was above the threshold for Endangered but below the threshold for Critically Endangered, thus under this criterion this Macrogroup is considered Endangered</Rationale>             </Rationales>             <Category>               <Category>EN</Category>             </Category>             <Subcriterions>               <Subcriterion name="A1">                 <Summaries>                   <Summary lang="en">We considered presence of trees (as closed forest or woodlands) as a characteristic element and the main indicator of spatial distribution of the macrogroup. Historical changes in forest cover were measured by contrasting series of reconstructed land cover classes for 1700, 1800, 1900 and 2000. We used woodland cover to estimate changes in forest cover. The proportional rate of decline (PRD) was estimated by interpolation of the area in the four time frames assuming a quadratic response curve to describe increasing or decreasing rates in the last 100 years. Mean estimated decline was 30 (5.4 -- 48.2) %, and it did not reach any of the thresholds for Vulnerable.</Summary>                 </Summaries>                 <Rationales>                   <Rationale lang="en">Mean estimated decline was 30 (5.4 -- 48.2) %, and it did not reach any of the thresholds for Vulnerable.</Rationale>                 </Rationales>                 <Category>LC</Category>                 <Plausible-bounds lower="LC" upper="VU">LC -- VU</Plausible-bounds>                 <Key-indicator-variables>                   <Key-indicator name="Change in distribution">                     <Indicator-data-values>                       <Indicator-data>                         <Data-descriptions>                           <Data-description lang="en">Changes in forest cover were measured by contrasting series of spatial layers from different sources of global extent. For historical representation of forest cover we used the Anthrome products (http://ecotope.org/anthromes/v2/data/, v 2.0, Ellis et al. 2010)⁠ which represent the reconstructed extent of different land cover classes for 1700, 1800, 1900 and 2000. We reclassified the layers and focused on woodland cover independent of use intensity (wild, used, populated and residential woodlands) to estimate changes in forest cover. The reclassified maps were crossed with the potential distribution of each Macrogroup in order to obtain an area estimate for each Macrogroup and each time-frame. The proportional rate of decline (PRD) was estimated by interpolation of the area in the four time frames assuming a quadratic response curve to describe increasing or decreasing rates in the last 100 years. The curve was fitted with a generalized linear model fitted using a quasipoisson error distribution and a log-link to avoid negative estimates of area. For this subcriterion we used the curve to estimate the PRD between 1950 and 2000.</Data-description>                         </Data-descriptions>                         <Data-source>Ellis, E.C., Goldewijk, K.K., Siebert, S., Lightman, D. and Ramankutty, N. (2010). Anthropogenic transformation of the biomes, 1700 to 2000. Glob. Ecol. Biogeogr., 19, 589–606.</Data-source>                         <Values method="estimated">                           <Value level="1">                             <Year>1950</Year>                             <Indicator-value units="km2"></Indicator-value>                           </Value>                           <Value level="2">                             <Year>2000</Year>                             <Indicator-value units="km2"></Indicator-value>                           </Value>                         </Values>                       </Indicator-data>                     </Indicator-data-values>                     <Overall-Extent units="%" method="estimated">30</Overall-Extent>                     <Collapse-threshold units="km2">0</Collapse-threshold>                   </Key-indicator>                 </Key-indicator-variables>               </Subcriterion>               <Subcriterion name="A2a">                 <Summaries>                   <Summary lang="en">The data used to estimate decline in distribution was not applied to this timeframe. Alternative prediction or forecast models need to be considered for assessing this subcriterion.</Summary>                 </Summaries>                 <Rationales>                   <Rationale lang="en">No suitable indicator was evaluated for this period of time.</Rationale>                 </Rationales>                 <Category>NE</Category>               </Subcriterion>               <Subcriterion name="A2b">                 <Summaries>                   <Summary lang="en">We considered presence of trees (as closed forest or woodlands) as a characteristic element and the main indicator of spatial distribution of the macrogroup. For contemporary forest cover we averaged percent tree cover from two time series of remote sensing data for each year between 2001 and 2012, and we calculated the proportional rate of decline (PRD) and used the difference in the predicted forest cover in 2001 and 2051 as an estimate of expected decline in any 50 year period including past, present and future.  Mean estimated decline was 59.2 (44.2 -- 70.2) %, exceeding the threshold for Endangered, but below the threshold for Critically Endangered.</Summary>                 </Summaries>                 <Rationales>                   <Rationale lang="en">Mean estimated decline was 59.2 (44.2 -- 70.2) %, exceeding the threshold for Endangered, but below the threshold for Critically Endangered.</Rationale>                 </Rationales>                 <Category>EN</Category>                 <Plausible-bounds lower="EN" upper="VU">EN -- VU</Plausible-bounds>                 <Key-indicator-variables>                   <Key-indicator name="Change in distribution">                     <Indicator-data-values>                       <Indicator-data>                         <Data-descriptions>                           <Data-description lang="en">For contemporary forest cover we considered two time series of data: the Global Forest Cover based on Landsat mosaics (GFC, version 1.2, Hansen et al. 2013)⁠  and the land cover data derived from MODIS  (MODIS LC, version 5.1, Friedl et al. 2010)⁠⁠. GFC data represents estimates of percentage tree cover in 2000 and estimates of forest loss and gain between 2000 and 2014, from which we calculated total forest cover per year. MODIS LC data represents yearly estimates of land cover classes between 2001 and 2012, including several forest types, semi-natural and artificial land cover. We converted land cover classes to percentage tree cover (100% for natural forest classes, 25% for mosaic vegetation, 0% otherwise). We then averaged percent tree cover from both sources for each year between 2001 and 2012 in order to partially correct over- and under-estimation of forest change due to increases in plantations and other artificial land uses (Song et al. 2014; Tropek et al. 2014)⁠. The estimated percentage tree cover of each year was summarized over the potential distribution of each Macrogroup to provide annual estimates of forest cover. The proportional rate of decline (PRD) was estimated by a generalized linear model fitted to the estimates per year using a quasipoisson error distribution and a log-link. For Macrogroups with a negative trend, the model  was used to predict the expected remaining distribution in 50 years. The use of this model avoids negative estimates of the remaining distribution. </Data-description>                         </Data-descriptions>                         <Data-source>Hansen et al. 2013</Data-source>                         <Data-source>Friedl et al. 2010</Data-source>                         <Values method="projected">                           <Value level="1">                             <Year>2000</Year>                             <Indicator-value units="km2"></Indicator-value>                           </Value>                           <Value level="2">                             <Year>2050</Year>                             <Indicator-value units="km2"></Indicator-value>                           </Value>                         </Values>                       </Indicator-data>                     </Indicator-data-values>                     <Overall-Extent units="%" method="projected">59.2</Overall-Extent>                     <Collapse-threshold units="km2">0</Collapse-threshold>                   </Key-indicator>                 </Key-indicator-variables>               </Subcriterion>               <Subcriterion name="A3">                 <Summaries>                   <Summary lang="en">We considered presence of trees (as closed forest or woodlands) as a characteristic element and the main indicator of spatial distribution of the macrogroup. Historical changes in forest cover were measured by contrasting series of reconstructed land cover classes for 1700, 1800, 1900 and 2000. We used woodland cover to estimate changes in forest cover. The proportional rate of decline (PRD) was estimated by interpolation of the area in the four time frames assuming a quadratic response curve to describe increasing or decreasing rates in the last 400 years. Mean estimated decline was 73 (61.1 -- 81.2) %, exceeding the threshold for Endangered, but below the threshold for Critically Endangered.</Summary>                 </Summaries>                 <Rationales>                   <Rationale lang="en">Mean estimated decline was 73 (61.1 -- 81.2) %, exceeding the threshold for Endangered, but below the threshold for Critically Endangered.</Rationale>                 </Rationales>                 <Category>EN</Category>                 <Plausible-bounds lower="VU" upper="EN">VU -- EN</Plausible-bounds>                 <Key-indicator-variables>                   <Key-indicator name="Change in distribution">                     <Indicator-data-values>                       <Indicator-data>                         <Data-descriptions>                           <Data-description lang="en">Changes in forest cover were measured by contrasting series of spatial layers from different sources of global extent. For historical representation of forest cover we used the Anthrome products (http://ecotope.org/anthromes/v2/data/, v 2.0, Ellis et al. 2010)⁠ which represent the reconstructed extent of different land cover classes for 1700, 1800, 1900 and 2000. We reclassified the layers and focused on woodland cover independent of use intensity (wild, used, populated and residential woodlands) to estimate changes in forest cover. The reclassified maps were crossed with the potential distribution of each Macrogroup in order to obtain an area estimate for each Macrogroup and each time-frame. The proportional rate of decline (PRD) was estimated by interpolation of the area in the four time frames assuming a quadratic response curve to describe increasing or decreasing rates in the last 400 years. The curve was fitted with a generalized linear model fitted using a quasipoisson error distribution and a log-link to avoid negative estimates of area. For this subcriterion we used the curve to estimate the PRD between 1750 and 2000.</Data-description>                         </Data-descriptions>                         <Data-source>Ellis, E.C., Goldewijk, K.K., Siebert, S., Lightman, D. and Ramankutty, N. (2010). Anthropogenic transformation of the biomes, 1700 to 2000. Glob. Ecol. Biogeogr., 19, 589–606.</Data-source>                         <Values method="estimated">                           <Value level="1">                             <Year>1750</Year>                             <Indicator-value units="km2"></Indicator-value>                           </Value>                           <Value level="2">                             <Year>2000</Year>                             <Indicator-value units="km2"></Indicator-value>                           </Value>                         </Values>                       </Indicator-data>                     </Indicator-data-values>                     <Overall-Extent units="%" method="estimated">73</Overall-Extent>                     <Collapse-threshold units="km2">0</Collapse-threshold>                   </Key-indicator>                 </Key-indicator-variables>               </Subcriterion>             </Subcriterions>           </Criterion>           <Criterion name="B">             <Summaries>               <Summary lang="en">We considered presence of trees (as closed forest or woodlands) as a characteristic element and the main indicator of spatial distribution of the macrogroup. For contemporary forest cover we overlaped the potential macrogroup distribution with an averaged percent tree cover from two time series of remote sensing data for the year 2012. We used a cutoff value of 25% tree cover to determine presence, and estimated the extent of occurrence using a convex hull polygon, and area of occupancy using a 10x10 grid. None of the assessed subcriteria met the threshold for Vulnerable, and under this criterion this Macrogroup is considered Least Concern</Summary>             </Summaries>             <Rationales>               <Rationale lang="en">None of the assessed subcriteria met the threshold for Vulnerable, and under this criterion this Macrogroup is considered Least Concern</Rationale>             </Rationales>             <Category>               <Category>LC</Category>             </Category>             <Subcriterions>               <Subcriterion name="B1">                 <Summaries>                   <Summary lang="en">We considered presence of trees (as closed forest or woodlands) as a characteristic element and the main indicator of spatial distribution of the macrogroup. For contemporary forest cover we overlaped the potential macrogroup distribution with an averaged percent tree cover from two time series of remote sensing data for the year 2012. We used a cutoff value of 25% tree cover to determine presence, and estimated the extent of occurrence as the minimum convex polygon around the presence data.  The Extent of Occurrence was larger that 50,000 km^2, so it is considered Least Concern.</Summary>                 </Summaries>                 <Rationales>                   <Rationale lang="en">The Extent of Occurrence was larger that 50,000 km^2, so it is considered Least Concern.</Rationale>                 </Rationales>                 <Category>LC</Category>                 <Key-indicator-variables>                   <Key-indicator name="EOO">                     <Indicator-data-values>                       <Indicator-data>                         <Data-descriptions>                           <Data-description lang="en">For contemporary forest cover we considered two time series of data: the Global Forest Cover based on Landsat mosaics (GFC, version 1.2, Hansen et al. 2013)⁠  and the land cover data derived from MODIS  (MODIS LC, version 5.1, Friedl et al. 2010)⁠⁠. GFC data represents estimates of percentage tree cover in 2000 and estimates of forest loss and gain between 2000 and 2014, from which we calculated total forest cover per year. MODIS LC data represents yearly estimates of land cover classes between 2001 and 2012, including several forest types, semi-natural and artificial land cover. We converted land cover classes to percentage tree cover (100% for natural forest classes, 25% for mosaic vegetation, 0% otherwise). We then averaged percent tree cover from both sources for each year between 2001 and 2012 in order to partially correct over- and under-estimation of forest change due to increases in plantations and other artificial land uses (Song et al. 2014; Tropek et al. 2014)⁠. We used a cutoff value of 25% tree cover to determine presence, and estimated the extent of occurrence as the minimum convex polygon around the presence data. </Data-description>                         </Data-descriptions>                         <Data-source>Hansen et al. 2013</Data-source>                         <Data-source>Friedl et al. 2010</Data-source>                         <Values method="estimated">                           <Value level="1">                             <Year>2012</Year>                             <Indicator-value units="km2"> greater than 50000</Indicator-value>                           </Value>                         </Values>                       </Indicator-data>                     </Indicator-data-values>                     <Overall-Extent units="km2" method="estimated"></Overall-Extent>                     <Collapse-threshold units="km2">0</Collapse-threshold>                   </Key-indicator>                 </Key-indicator-variables>                 <Threat-defined-locations>More than 10</Threat-defined-locations>                 <Continuing-decline numeral="i">yes</Continuing-decline>                 <Threatening-process>yes</Threatening-process>               </Subcriterion>               <Subcriterion name="B2">                 <Summaries>                   <Summary lang="en">We considered presence of trees (as closed forest or woodlands) as a characteristic element and the main indicator of spatial distribution of the macrogroup. For contemporary forest cover we overlaped the potential macrogroup distribution with an averaged percent tree cover from two time series of remote sensing data for the year 2012. We used a cutoff value of 25% tree cover to determine presence, and counted the number of 10x10 km cells that had at least 1% of their area occupied the the ecosystem.  The Area of Occupancy was larger that 50 10x10 km grid cells, so it is considered Least Concern.</Summary>                 </Summaries>                 <Rationales>                   <Rationale lang="en">The Area of Occupancy was larger that 50 10x10 km grid cells, so it is considered Least Concern.</Rationale>                 </Rationales>                 <Category>LC</Category>                 <Key-indicator-variables>                   <Key-indicator name="AOO">                     <Indicator-data-values>                       <Indicator-data>                         <Data-descriptions>                           <Data-description lang="en">For contemporary forest cover we considered two time series of data: the Global Forest Cover based on Landsat mosaics (GFC, version 1.2, Hansen et al. 2013)⁠  and the land cover data derived from MODIS  (MODIS LC, version 5.1, Friedl et al. 2010)⁠⁠. GFC data represents estimates of percentage tree cover in 2000 and estimates of forest loss and gain between 2000 and 2014, from which we calculated total forest cover per year. MODIS LC data represents yearly estimates of land cover classes between 2001 and 2012, including several forest types, semi-natural and artificial land cover. We converted land cover classes to percentage tree cover (100% for natural forest classes, 25% for mosaic vegetation, 0% otherwise). We then averaged percent tree cover from both sources for each year between 2001 and 2012 in order to partially correct over- and under-estimation of forest change due to increases in plantations and other artificial land uses (Song et al. 2014; Tropek et al. 2014)⁠. We used a cutoff value of 25% tree cover to determine presence, overlaped this with a 10x10 km grid, and counted the number of 10x10 km cells that had at least 1% of their area occupied the the ecosystem.</Data-description>                         </Data-descriptions>                         <Data-source>Hansen et al. 2013</Data-source>                         <Data-source>Friedl et al. 2010</Data-source>                         <Values method="estimated">                           <Value level="1">                             <Year>2012</Year>                             <Indicator-value units="10x10km cells"> greater than 50</Indicator-value>                           </Value>                         </Values>                       </Indicator-data>                     </Indicator-data-values>                     <Overall-Extent units="10x10km cells" method="estimated"></Overall-Extent>                     <Collapse-threshold units="km2">0</Collapse-threshold>                   </Key-indicator>                 </Key-indicator-variables>                 <Threat-defined-locations>More than 10</Threat-defined-locations>                 <Continuing-decline numeral="i">yes</Continuing-decline>                 <Threatening-process>yes</Threatening-process>               </Subcriterion>               <Subcriterion name="B3">                 <Summaries>                   <Summary lang="en">We considered presence of trees (as closed forest or woodlands) as a characteristic element and the main indicator of spatial distribution of the macrogroup. Threat defined locations and threatening processes were assesed qualitatively.  This ecosystem is present at a large number of locations and not exposed to severe and widespread threats, it was considered Least Concern.</Summary>                 </Summaries>                 <Rationales>                   <Rationale lang="en">This ecosystem is present at a large number of locations and not exposed to severe and widespread threats, it was considered Least Concern.</Rationale>                 </Rationales>                 <Category>LC</Category>                 <Plausible-bounds lower="" upper=""></Plausible-bounds>                 <Threat-defined-locations>More than 10</Threat-defined-locations>                 <Continuing-decline numeral="i">yes</Continuing-decline>                 <Threatening-process>yes</Threatening-process>               </Subcriterion>             </Subcriterions>           </Criterion>           <Criterion name="C">             <Summaries>               <Summary lang="en">Climate conditions are generally considered of great importance for the maintainance of forest vegetation and characteristic processes of several macrogroups, and were also incorporated in the process of macrogroup potential distribution modeling and validation. Thus we considered climate change as a plausible future threat of degradation of environmental conditions. Natural disturbances are considered within the IVC classification as processes influencing the dominant and characteristic growth forms and diagnostic species of formations, and can be greatly altered by human activities⁠. Flood and fire regimes play an important role in forest formations, but we did not find a reliable indicator for changes in fire regime at the continental scale. Flood regime was not considered to be relevant to this ecosystem and was not evaluated.</Summary>             </Summaries>             <Rationales>               <Rationale lang="en">None of the assessed subcriteria met the threshold for Vulnerable, and under this criterion this Macrogroup is considered Least Concern</Rationale>             </Rationales>             <Category>               <Category>LC</Category>             </Category>             <Subcriterions>               <Subcriterion name="C1">                 <Summaries>                   <Summary lang="en">The data used to estimate deterioration of environmental conditions was relevant to present and future  time frames, but not applicable to historic or past time frames. Alternative data sources need to be considered for assessing this subcriterion.</Summary>                 </Summaries>                 <Rationales>                   <Rationale lang="en">No suitable indicator was evaluated for this period of time.</Rationale>                 </Rationales>                 <Category>NE</Category>               </Subcriterion>               <Subcriterion name="C2a">                 <Summaries>                   <Summary lang="en">We considered climate change as a plausible future threat of degradation of environmental conditions as it might influence both the predominant growth form and characteristic biota. We used a set of 19 standard bioclimatic variables as indicators of characteristic environmental conditions (Hijmans et al. 2005)⁠ and used a Random Forest Classification algorithm to evaluate suitability of environmental conditions under current climate and future projections based on climate change models. We evaluated the probability of the target macrogroup to be replaced by any forest or non-forest vegetation macrogroup under changing climatic conditions. Mean relative severity was 28.2 (23.5 -- 29.7) %, and it did not reach any of the thresholds for Vulnerable.</Summary>                 </Summaries>                 <Rationales>                   <Rationale lang="en">Mean relative severity was 28.2 (23.5 -- 29.7) %, and it did not reach any of the thresholds for Vulnerable.</Rationale>                 </Rationales>                 <Category>LC</Category>                 <Plausible-bounds lower="LC" upper="NT">LC--NT</Plausible-bounds>                 <Key-indicator-variables>                   <Key-indicator name="Changes in climate conditions">                     <Indicator-data-values>                       <Indicator-data>                         <Data-descriptions>                           <Data-description lang="en">We selected a group of 19 standard bioclimatic variables as indicators of overall environmental conditions  and compared current and future conditions. “Current” climate is based on interpolation of weather station data from a reference time frame between 1960 and 1990 (Worldclim, v1.4; Hijmans et al. 2005)⁠; while future scenarios for the year 2050 were calculated for different combinations of global circulation models (GCM) and representative concentration pathways (RCP; IPCC 2014)⁠. All data was available in the same format, resolution and from the same source (http://worldclim.org). We used the *random forest* (RF) algorithm, which is a machine learning method based on an ensemble of classification trees (Liaw and Wiener 2002)⁠ to predict changes from a focal macrogroup to any of the associated forest or non-forest macrogroups. First we define a bounding box around each target macrogroup, and take a spatially uniform random sample of locations. For each location we record the potential macrogroup according to the potential distribution map and the values of the 19 bioclimatic variables. We partition the data in calibration and test subsets (75 and 25% of the locations respectively) using a checkerboard pattern to reduce spatial autocorrelation⁠. Then we fitted the RF model with the calibration data, sample size for each classification tree was set to 2/3 of the calibration data, but allowing for a representative sample of all represented classes, number of variables per tree was set to five, other setting were set to default values. Models were considered accepted if nominal classification error for the focal class was lower than 20% in the test samples, and the area under the sensitivity and specificity curve (AUC) was higher than 85%. The first statistic measures the misclassification when using the modal class from the ensemble prediction which can be a combination of model performance error and natural overlap between related classes⁠, the second one measures discrimination performance when considering only the focal class and  different threshold of model support (proportion of “votes”, or proportion of classification trees assigning the focal class). Future prediction was only attempted when model performance on current data was acceptable. Future predictions were performed for each set of future bioclimatic conditions corresponding to five GCM (BCC-CSM1-1, CCSM4, HadGEM2-AO, HadGEM2-ES and MIROC5) and four RCP (rcp26, rcp45, rcp60 and rcp85). In order to calculate relative severity for the indicator of changing climatic conditions over the whole bounding box we used RF-model prediction (as proportion of votes for the focal class) as a measure of appropriate climatic conditions for the focal macrogroup, and considered the threshold for equal specificity and sensitivity as the threshold at which environmental conditions shift to favor a different macrogroup (collapse threshold, CT). We compared predictions based on current climatic condition (initial value) and predictions based on each combination of GCM and RCP for 2050 (final value). We summarized the results of the 20 combinations of GCMs and RCP to calculate the best estimate and plausible bounds (range including 90% probabilities) for the threat category (Bland et al. 2017)⁠. This indicator measures the expected decline for the next 50 years and thus corresponds to subcriterion C2a.</Data-description>                         </Data-descriptions>                         <Data-source>Hijmans et al. 2005</Data-source>                         <Data-source>Liaw and Wiener 2002</Data-source>                         <Values method="projected">                           <Value level="1">                             <Year>2050</Year>                             <Indicator-value units=""/>                             <Extent units="%">43.6</Extent>                             <Severity units="%"> greater than 30</Severity>                           </Value>                           <Value level="2">                             <Year>2050</Year>                             <Indicator-value units=""/>                             <Extent units="%">32.8</Extent>                             <Severity units="%"> greater than 50</Severity>                           </Value>                           <Value level="3">                             <Year>2050</Year>                             <Indicator-value units=""/>                             <Extent units="%">5.6</Extent>                             <Severity units="%"> greater than 80</Severity>                           </Value>                         </Values>                       </Indicator-data>                     </Indicator-data-values>                     <Overall-Extent units="%" method="projected">100</Overall-Extent>                     <Overall-Severity units="%" method="projected">28.2</Overall-Severity>                     <Collapse-threshold units="">We considered the threshold for equal specificity and sensitivity as the threshold at which environmental conditions shift to favor a different macrogroup.</Collapse-threshold>                   </Key-indicator>                 </Key-indicator-variables>               </Subcriterion>               <Subcriterion name="C2b">                 <Summaries>                   <Summary lang="en">The data used to estimate deterioration of environmental conditions was relevant to future  time frames, but not applicable to present, historic or past time frames. Alternative data sources need to be considered for assessing this subcriterion.</Summary>                 </Summaries>                 <Rationale>This subcriterion was not evaluated.</Rationale>                 <Category>NE</Category>               </Subcriterion>               <Subcriterion name="C3">                 <Summaries>                   <Summary lang="en">The data used to estimate deterioration of environmental conditions was relevant to present and future  time frames, but not applicable to historic or past time frames. Alternative data sources need to be considered for assessing this subcriterion.</Summary>                 </Summaries>                 <Rationales>                   <Rationale lang="en">No suitable indicator was evaluated for this period of time.</Rationale>                 </Rationales>                 <Category>NE</Category>               </Subcriterion>             </Subcriterions>           </Criterion>           <Criterion name="D">             <Summaries>               <Summary lang="en">For criterion D we considered that large vertebrates (and specially large mammals) are a characteristic component of forests, and their due to overexploitation has an impact in important biotic associations in ecosystems (Galetti and Dirzo 2013; Dirzo et al. 2014)⁠.  We used recent estimates of hunting-depletion distances to assess potential ecosystem degradation severity and extent in tropical regions (Benítez-López et al. 2017)⁠. We did not find reliable indicators of other important threatening processes like invasive species or selective logging at a continental scale, but we considered that increased human use intensity could be used as indirect indicator of those (Ellis et al. 2010).</Summary>             </Summaries>             <Rationales>               <Rationale lang="en">Subcriterion D3 was above the threshold for Vulnerable but below the threshold for Endangered, thus under this criterion this Macrogroup is considered Vulnerable</Rationale>             </Rationales>             <Category>               <Category>VU</Category>             </Category>             <Subcriterions>               <Subcriterion name="D1">                 <Summaries>                   <Summary lang="en">We estimate changes in resource use intensity by reclassifying the reconstructed land cover classes for 1900 and 2000 from the Anthrome products (Ellis et al. 2010). We crossed the potential distribution of the Macrogroup with the distinct woodland cover classes, and calculated the proportion of area that changed between the two Anthromes layers from low intensity ('wild woodlands' or 'used woodlands') to high intensity of use ('populated woodlands' or 'residential woodlands'). Mean relative severity was 5.6 %, and it did not reach any of the thresholds for Vulnerable.</Summary>                 </Summaries>                 <Rationales>                   <Rationale lang="en">Mean relative severity was 5.6 %, and it did not reach any of the thresholds for Vulnerable.</Rationale>                 </Rationales>                 <Category>LC</Category>                 <Key-indicator-variables>                   <Key-indicator name="Resource use intensity">                     <Indicator-data-values>                       <Indicator-data>                         <Data-descriptions>                           <Data-description lang="en">We estimate changes in resource use intensity by reclassifying the reconstructed land cover classes for 1900 and 2000 from the Anthrome products (Ellis et al. 2010). We crossed the potential distribution of the Macrogroup with the distinct woodland cover classes, and calculated the proportion of area that changed between the two Anthromes layers from low intensity ('wild woodlands' or 'used woodlands') to high intensity of use ('populated woodlands' or 'residential woodlands'). We assume that the class 'Natural woodlands' represents natural conditions and the other classes represent increasing amounts of disruption leading to collapse ('Natural'  less than  'Used'  less than  'Populated'  less than  'Residential'). We considered equal step weights for changes between consecutive classes, thus a change from 'Natural' to 'Used' or from 'Used' to 'Populated' was represented as RS=25%, while a change from 'Natural' to 'Populated' or from 'Used' to 'Residential' would be represented by RS=50%, etc. We do not have a quantitative estimate of collapse, but assume that the class 'Natural woodlands' represents natural conditions and the other classes represent increasing amounts of disruption leading to collapse ('Natural'  less than  'Used'  less than  'Populated'  less than  'Residential').</Data-description>                         </Data-descriptions>                         <Data-source>Ellis, E.C., Goldewijk, K.K., Siebert, S., Lightman, D. and Ramankutty, N. (2010). Anthropogenic transformation of the biomes, 1700 to 2000. Glob. Ecol. Biogeogr., 19, 589–606.</Data-source>                         <Values method="inferred">                           <Value level="1">                             <Year>2000</Year>                             <Indicator-value units=""/>                             <Extent units="%">21.6</Extent>                             <Severity units="%"> greater than 30</Severity>                           </Value>                           <Value level="2">                             <Year>2000</Year>                             <Indicator-value units=""/>                             <Extent units="%">0.5</Extent>                             <Severity units="%"> greater than 50</Severity>                           </Value>                           <Value level="3">                             <Year>2000</Year>                             <Indicator-value units=""/>                             <Extent units="%">0.2</Extent>                             <Severity units="%"> greater than 80</Severity>                           </Value>                         </Values>                       </Indicator-data>                     </Indicator-data-values>                     <Overall-Extent units="%" method="inferred">100</Overall-Extent>                     <Overall-Severity units="%" method="inferred">5.6</Overall-Severity>                     <Collapse-threshold units="%"></Collapse-threshold>                   </Key-indicator>                 </Key-indicator-variables>               </Subcriterion>               <Subcriterion name="D2a">                 <Summaries>                   <Summary lang="en"/>                 </Summaries>                 <Rationales>                   <Rationale lang="en">No suitable indicator was evaluated for this period of time.</Rationale>                 </Rationales>                 <Category/>               </Subcriterion>               <Subcriterion name="D2b">                 <Summaries>                   <Summary lang="en"/>                 </Summaries>                 <Rationales>                   <Rationale lang="en"/>                 </Rationales>                 <Category>DD</Category>                 <Key-indicator-variables>                   <Key-indicator name="Potential defaunation">                     <Indicator-data-values>                       <Indicator-data>                         <Data-descriptions>                           <Data-description lang="en">We applied a simplified formula relating response ratios (RR) of the abundance of mammals in hunted and unhunted sites with three variables: distance to access points for hunters (approximated by distance in km to the  main road network, from Digital Chart of the World), distance to markets for wildlife products (approximated by the distance in km to major urban centers, calculated from urban land cover in MODIS LC, version 5.1, Friedl et al. 2010)⁠ and level of protection (approximated by the distribution of any kind of protected areas, from the World Database on Protected Areas, IUCN and UNEP-WCMC 2016). According to figures and detailed results from (Benítez-López et al. 2017)⁠⁠, we used the following formula to estimate the expected RR from raster images representing the three variables: RR = -2.370 + 0.057 access + 0.010 market + 1.270 protected . We then transformed the spatial estimate of RR to an estimate of potential decline in mammal abundance as a percentage . For negative RR values we estimated the decline as: decline = (1-exp(RR)) * 100. For zero or positive RR values we assumed zero decline. An overall weighted estimate of percentage decline was calculated over the potential distribution of each Macrogroup, using mean forest cover between 2001 and 2012 as a weighting variable. We assume that the applied formula represents the potential relative decline in mammal abundance and used a collapse threshold equivalent of 10% of the original abundance. We further assume that the formula represents a current level of threat representative a 50 year window including past, present and future.</Data-description>                         </Data-descriptions>                         <Data-source>Benítez-López, A., Alkemade, J.R.M., Schipper, A.M., Ingram, D.J., Verweij, P.A., Eikelboom, J. and Huijbregts, M. (2017). The impact of hunting on tropical mammal and bird populations. Science (80-. )., 356, 180–183.</Data-source>                         <Data-source>Digital Chart of the World: road network per country</Data-source>                         <Data-source>Friedl, M.A., Sulla-Menashe, D., Tan, B., Schneider, A., Ramankutty, N., Sibley, A. and Huang, X. (2010). MODIS Collection 5 global land cover: Algorithm refinements and characterization of new datasets, 2001-2012, Collection 5.1 IGBP Land Cover.</Data-source>                         <Data-source>World Database on Protected Areas, IUCN and UNEP-WCMC 2016</Data-source>                         <Values method="inferred">                           <Value level="1">                             <Year>2000</Year>                             <Indicator-value units=""></Indicator-value>                           </Value>                         </Values>                       </Indicator-data>                     </Indicator-data-values>                     <Overall-Extent units="%" method="inferred">100</Overall-Extent>                     <Overall-Severity units="%" method="inferred"></Overall-Severity>                     <Collapse-threshold units="% of the original abundance">10</Collapse-threshold>                   </Key-indicator>                 </Key-indicator-variables>               </Subcriterion>               <Subcriterion name="D3">                 <Summaries>                   <Summary lang="en">We estimate changes in resource use intensity by reclassifying the reconstructed land cover classes for 1700 and 2000 from the Anthrome products (Ellis et al. 2010). We crossed the potential distribution of the Macrogroup with the distinct woodland cover classes, and calculated the proportion of area that changed between the two Anthromes layers from low intensity ('wild woodlands' or 'used woodlands') to high intensity of use ('populated woodlands' or 'residential woodlands'). Mean relative severity was 52.6. 85.7 % of the extent had a relative severity of 50 % or higher, exceeding the threshold for Vulnerable.</Summary>                 </Summaries>                 <Rationales>                   <Rationale lang="en">Mean relative severity was 52.6. 85.7 % of the extent had a relative severity of 50 % or higher, exceeding the threshold for Vulnerable.</Rationale>                 </Rationales>                 <Category>VU</Category>                 <Key-indicator-variables>                   <Key-indicator name="Resource use intensity">                     <Indicator-data-values>                       <Indicator-data>                         <Data-descriptions>                           <Data-description lang="en">We estimate changes in resource use intensity by reclassifying the reconstructed land cover classes for 1700 and 2000 from the Anthrome products (Ellis et al. 2010). We crossed the potential distribution of the Macrogroup with the distinct woodland cover classes, and calculated the proportion of area that changed between the two Anthromes layers from low intensity ('wild woodlands' or 'used woodlands') to high intensity of use ('populated woodlands' or 'residential woodlands'). We assume that the class 'Natural woodlands' represents natural conditions and the other classes represent increasing amounts of disruption leading to collapse ('Natural'  less than  'Used'  less than  'Populated'  less than  'Residential'). We considered equal step weights for changes between consecutive classes, thus a change from 'Natural' to 'Used' or from 'Used' to 'Populated' was represented as RS=25%, while a change from 'Natural' to 'Populated' or from 'Used' to 'Residential' would be represented by RS=50%, etc. We do not have a quantitative estimate of collapse, but assume that the class 'Natural woodlands' represents natural conditions and the other classes represent increasing amounts of disruption leading to collapse ('Natural'  less than  'Used'  less than  'Populated'  less than  'Residential').</Data-description>                         </Data-descriptions>                         <Data-source>Ellis, E.C., Goldewijk, K.K., Siebert, S., Lightman, D. and Ramankutty, N. (2010). Anthropogenic transformation of the biomes, 1700 to 2000. Glob. Ecol. Biogeogr., 19, 589–606.</Data-source>                         <Values method="inferred">                           <Value level="1">                             <Year>2000</Year>                             <Indicator-value units=""/>                             <Extent units="%">85.7</Extent>                             <Severity units="%"> greater than 50</Severity>                           </Value>                           <Value level="2">                             <Year>2000</Year>                             <Indicator-value units=""/>                             <Extent units="%">26.4</Extent>                             <Severity units="%"> greater than 70</Severity>                           </Value>                           <Value level="3">                             <Year>2000</Year>                             <Indicator-value units=""/>                             <Extent units="%">0</Extent>                             <Severity units="%"> greater than 90</Severity>                           </Value>                         </Values>                       </Indicator-data>                     </Indicator-data-values>                     <Overall-Extent units="%" method="inferred">100</Overall-Extent>                     <Overall-Severity units="%" method="inferred">52.6</Overall-Severity>                     <Collapse-threshold units="%"></Collapse-threshold>                   </Key-indicator>                 </Key-indicator-variables>               </Subcriterion>             </Subcriterions>           </Criterion>           <Criterion name="E">             <Summaries>               <Summary lang="en">No quantitative assessment of ecosystem collapse was performed for this assessment unit.</Summary>             </Summaries>             <Rationales>               <Rationale lang="en">This criterion was not evaluated.</Rationale>             </Rationales>             <Category>NE</Category>           </Criterion>         </Criterions>       </Assessment-unit>     </Ecosystem-Risk-Assessment>     <Content-Curations>       <content-curation date="2020-04-30" updated-by="Rsaurio" status="auto-generated-test">         <edit-description>XML document generation through R-scripts</edit-description>       </content-curation>     </Content-Curations>   </Case-Study> </Case-Studies>
