<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <Case-Studies><Case-Study name="Forest Macrogroups of the Americas: '1.B.1.Ef.652 - Central Chilean (Mediterranean) Sclerophyllous Forest, EN (EN -- CR)'" id="FerrerParis_Continental_ForestMacrogroup_2017_3"><Case-Study-Names/><Scope><Scope-description>The risk assessment covered the entire distribution of the assessment target as described by the classification scheme and distribution maps available.</Scope-description><Scope-classification id="IUCN RLE" version="1.0" selected="yes" assigned-by="JRFEP"><Scope-classification-element level="1">1. Global</Scope-classification-element></Scope-classification></Scope><Assessment-Information date="2019-09-30" reviewer="Rsaurio" status="auto-generated-test" load="false"><ref-label>FerrerParis_Continental_ForestMacrogroup_2017</ref-label><Assessment-updated></Assessment-updated><Assessment-authors><Author>JR Ferrer-Paris</Author><Author>I Zager</Author></Assessment-authors><Assessment-collaborators><Collaborator>C. Josse</Collaborator><Collaborator>M. A. Oliveira‐Miranda</Collaborator><Collaborator>M. González‐Gil</Collaborator><Collaborator>D. Velarde</Collaborator><Collaborator>G. C. De La Cruz-Melo</Collaborator><Collaborator>E. Primiciero</Collaborator></Assessment-collaborators><Assessment-reviewers/><Keywords><Keyword>Woodlands</Keyword><Keyword>Climate change</Keyword><Keyword>Defaunation</Keyword><Keyword>Anthromes</Keyword><Keyword>Surface water</Keyword></Keywords></Assessment-Information><Assessment-Target date="2019-09-30" updated-by="Rsaurio" status="auto-generated-test"><AT-id>CARIB_Pine_Oak_Dry_Forest_3</AT-id><AT-descriptions><AT-description lang="en">The '1.B.1.Ef.652 - Central Chilean (Mediterranean) Sclerophyllous Forest' is a forest macrogroup belonging to the '1.B.1.Ef Chilean Mediterranean Forest' division in the International Vegetation Classification system (Faber-Langendoen et al. 2014). It is considered here as a proxy for a forest ecosystem type in a regional assessment of forest ecosystems in the Americas.</AT-description></AT-descriptions><AT-names><AT-name lang="en">1.B.1.Ef.652 - Central Chilean (Mediterranean) Sclerophyllous Forest</AT-name></AT-names><Characteristic-biota><Biota-Summaries><Biota-Summary lang="en">A list of 21 characteristic species was extracted from descriptive profiles of the Macrogroup.</Biota-Summary></Biota-Summaries><taxons><taxon lang="scientific">Cryptocarya alba</taxon><taxon lang="scientific">Peumus boldus Persea lingue</taxon><taxon lang="scientific">Lithrea caustica</taxon><taxon lang="scientific">Schinus latifolius</taxon><taxon lang="scientific">Beilshmiedia miersii</taxon><taxon lang="scientific">Crinodendron patagua</taxon><taxon lang="scientific">Quillaja saponaria</taxon><taxon lang="scientific">Colliguaja odorifera</taxon><taxon lang="scientific">Retanilla trineriva</taxon><taxon lang="scientific">Escallonia pulverulenta</taxon><taxon lang="scientific">Lobelia excelsa</taxon><taxon lang="scientific">Aextoxicon punctatum</taxon><taxon lang="scientific">Puya berteroniana</taxon><taxon lang="scientific">Echinopsis chiloensis</taxon><taxon lang="scientific">Jubaea chilensis</taxon><taxon lang="scientific">Kageneckia angustifolia</taxon><taxon lang="scientific">Guindilia trinervis</taxon><taxon lang="scientific">Colliguaja integerrima</taxon><taxon lang="scientific">Proustia cuneifolia</taxon><taxon lang="scientific">Satureja gilliesii</taxon><taxon lang="scientific">N.T.</taxon></taxons></Characteristic-biota><Abiotic-environment><Abiotic-Summaries><Abiotic-Summary lang="en">Information on soil and general climatic conditions was extracted from descriptive profiles of the Macrogroup.</Abiotic-Summary><Abiotic-Summary lang="es">Clima mediterraneo, de xerico a sub-humedo. </Abiotic-Summary></Abiotic-Summaries></Abiotic-environment><Biotic-processes><Processes-Summaries><Processes-Summary lang="en">Information on biotic characteristics and processes was extracted from descriptive profiles of the Macrogroup.</Processes-Summary><Processes-Summary lang="es">La estructura de los diferentes bosques esclerofilos depende de la humedad disponible, las zonas con mejor disponibilidad de humedad son los lugares frente al mar y en los valles, en estos lugares tienen alturas entre 8-12 m, diversos y con dosel casi cerrado y con alta presencia de epifitas vasculares. Los bosques esclerofilos montanos tienen un dosel abierto, tiene un diverso estrato arbustivo y las comunidades herbaceas son mas diversos y abundantes en zona de montaña. </Processes-Summary></Processes-Summaries></Biotic-processes><Ecosystem-services/><Threats/><Conservation-actions/><Research-needs/><Conceptual-ecosystem-model><CEM-summaries><CEM-summary lang="en">A general conceptual model is presented graphically in Fig. S1. We include in this model the most important large scale threats to forest in the Americas: loss of forest cover due to agriculture and live stock expansion; defaunation due to hunting (or 'empty forest syndrome'), structural and compositional changes due to selective logging and invasion of exotic species, changes in disturbance regimes due to land use practices and development and shifting climatic conditions due to climate change.</CEM-summary></CEM-summaries><CEM-type graphic="yes">Cause-effect</CEM-type><CEM-source>Assessment authors, based on Laurance and Williamson (2001), Allen et al. (2010), Faber-Langendoen et al. (2014), Lewis et al. (2015), Levis et al. (2017)</CEM-source></Conceptual-ecosystem-model><Classifications><Classification-system id="IUCN habitat" version="3.0" selected="yes" assigned-by="Assessment authors"><Classification-element level="1">1. Forest</Classification-element><Classification-element level="2">1.4. Forest – Temperate</Classification-element></Classification-system><Classification-system id="RLE Global Typology" version="draft" selected="no" assigned-by="Assessment authors"><Classification-element level="1">Terrestrial</Classification-element><Classification-element level="2">T2 Temperate-boreal forests and woodlands</Classification-element><Classification-element level="3">T2.2 Temperate deciduous forests and shrublands</Classification-element></Classification-system><Classification-system id="IVC" version="2014" selected="no" assigned-by="Assessment authors"><Classification-element level="1">1 Forest and Woodland</Classification-element><Classification-element level="2">1.B Temperate and Boreal Forest and Woodland</Classification-element><Classification-element level="3">1.B.1 Warm Temperate Forest &amp; Woodland</Classification-element><Classification-element level="4">1.B.1.Ef Chilean Mediterranean Forest</Classification-element><Classification-element level="5">1.B.1.Ef.652 - Central Chilean (Mediterranean) Sclerophyllous Forest</Classification-element></Classification-system></Classifications><Distribution><Distribution-Summaries><Distribution-Summary lang="es">Se presentan en la region central y sur de Chile, el rango altitudinal esta entre los 0 y 1300 msnm para los bosques distribuidos en la costa, valles centrales y colinas interiores de la cordillera de la Costa. Los bosques montanos se encuentran en el centro y laderas occidentales, se presentan entre los 1400-2200 msnm</Distribution-Summary></Distribution-Summaries><Biogeographic-realm>Neotropic</Biogeographic-realm><Spatial-data/></Distribution><Collapse-definition><Spatial-collapse lang="en">As the tree growth form is the main structural element of any forest macrogroup, a forest macrogroup was assumed to collapse if the original woodland cover was completely replaced by a non-woodland cover, or if the tree-cover within its potential distribution declined to zero (criteria A and B).</Spatial-collapse><Functional-collapse lang="en">For assessing environmental degradation under criterion C, we considered two different indicators. In the case of climate change, we assume that the ecosystem collapsed if the climatic conditions shifted from mostly suitable for the focus macrogroup, to mostly suitable to a different macrogroup. Additionally for flooded and swamp forest, we assumed ecosystem collapse if the amount of detected surface water within the potential distribution of the macrogroup declined to zero.  For assessing disruption to biotic processes and interactions under criterion D we assumed that most of the fundamental processes and interactions disappeared with intensive use of woodlands under high population density. We also assumed that the ecosystem would collapse if the population of large mammals declined to less than 10% of their original population size.</Functional-collapse></Collapse-definition></Assessment-Target><Ecosystem-Risk-Assessment date="2019-09-30" updated-by="Rsaurio" status="auto-generated-test"><Assessment-version>2.2</Assessment-version><Risk-assessment-protocol>IUCN RLE</Risk-assessment-protocol><Assessment-units><Assessment-unit><Ecosystem-subset><Subset-descriptions><Subset-description lang="en">This assessment refers to the entire distribution of the assessment target as delimited by the assessment authors.</Subset-description></Subset-descriptions><Countries><Country iso-code-2="CL">Chile</Country></Countries><Spatial-data><Spatial-point datum="WGS84" proj="longlat" type="lower-left-corner"><x>-73.1122059562123</x><y>-39.4166887020706</y><radius units="degrees">0.0001</radius></Spatial-point><Spatial-point datum="WGS84" proj="longlat" type="upper-right-corner"><x>-69.925763451613</x><y>-24.8875252254687</y><radius units="degrees">0.0001</radius></Spatial-point></Spatial-data></Ecosystem-subset><RA-Summaries/><Rationale/><Overall-category>EN</Overall-category><Plausible-bounds lower="EN" upper="CR"/><Supporting-subcriteria>A1+A3</Supporting-subcriteria><Criterions><Criterion name="A"/><Criterion name="B"/><Criterion name="C"><Summaries><Summary lang="en">Climate conditions are generally considered of great importance for the maintainance of forest vegetation and characteristic processes of several macrogroups, and were also incorporated in the process of macrogroup potential distribution modeling and validation. Thus we considered climate change as a plausible future threat of degradation of environmental conditions. Natural disturbances are considered within the IVC classification as processes influencing the dominant and characteristic growth forms and diagnostic species of formations, and can be greatly altered by human activities⁠. Flood and fire regimes play an important role in forest formations, but we did not find a reliable indicator for changes in fire regime at the continental scale. Flood regime was not considered to be relevant to this ecosystem and was not evaluated.</Summary></Summaries><Rationale name="C">Assessment outcome was not conclusive, thus under this criterion it is considered Data Deficient.</Rationale><Category><Category>DD</Category></Category><Subcriterions><Subcriterion name="C1"><Summaries><Summary lang="en">The data used to estimate deterioration of environmental conditions was relevant to present and future  time frames, but not applicable to historic or past time frames. Alternative data sources need to be considered for assessing this subcriterion.</Summary></Summaries><Rationale>No suitable indicator was evaluated for this period of time.</Rationale><Category>NE</Category></Subcriterion><Subcriterion name="C2a"><Summaries><Summary lang="en">We considered climate change as a plausible future threat of degradation of environmental conditions as it might influence both the predominant growth form and characteristic biota. We used a set of 19 standard bioclimatic variables as indicators of characteristic environmental conditions (Hijmans et al. 2005)⁠ and used a Random Forest Classification algorithm to evaluate suitability of environmental conditions under current climate and future projections based on climate change models. We evaluated the probability of the target macrogroup to be replaced by any forest or non-forest vegetation macrogroup under changing climatic conditions. Available data was not accurate enough, resulting in unreliable estimates, thus we assigned it to the Data Deficient category.</Summary></Summaries><Rationale>Available data was not accurate enough, resulting in unreliable estimates, thus we assigned it to the Data Deficient category.</Rationale><Category>DD</Category><Bounds></Bounds><Key-indicator-variable name="Changes in climate conditions"><Key-indicator><Indicator-data><Data-source>Hijmans et al. 2005</Data-source><Data-source>Liaw &amp; Wiener 2002</Data-source><Data-description>We selected a group of 19 standard bioclimatic variables as indicators of overall environmental conditions  and compared current and future conditions. “Current” climate is based on interpolation of weather station data from a reference time frame between 1960 and 1990 (Worldclim, v1.4; Hijmans et al. 2005)⁠; while future scenarios for the year 2050 were calculated for different combinations of global circulation models (GCM) and representative concentration pathways (RCP; IPCC 2014)⁠. All data was available in the same format, resolution and from the same source (http://worldclim.org). We used the *random forest* (RF) algorithm, which is a machine learning method based on an ensemble of classification trees (Liaw &amp; Wiener 2002)⁠ to predict changes from a focal macrogroup to any of the associated forest or non-forest macrogroups. First we define a bounding box around each target macrogroup, and take a spatially uniform random sample of locations. For each location we record the potential macrogroup according to the potential distribution map and the values of the 19 bioclimatic variables. We partition the data in calibration and test subsets (75 and 25% of the locations respectively) using a checkerboard pattern to reduce spatial autocorrelation⁠. Then we fitted the RF model with the calibration data, sample size for each classification tree was set to 2/3 of the calibration data, but allowing for a representative sample of all represented classes, number of variables per tree was set to five, other setting were set to default values. Models were considered accepted if nominal classification error for the focal class was lower than 20% in the test samples, and the area under the sensitivity and specificity curve (AUC) was higher than 85%. The first statistic measures the misclassification when using the modal class from the ensemble prediction which can be a combination of model performance error and natural overlap between related classes⁠, the second one measures discrimination performance when considering only the focal class and  different threshold of model support (proportion of “votes”, or proportion of classification trees assigning the focal class). Future prediction was only attempted when model performance on current data was acceptable. Future predictions were performed for each set of future bioclimatic conditions corresponding to five GCM (BCC-CSM1-1, CCSM4, HadGEM2-AO, HadGEM2-ES and MIROC5) and four RCP (rcp26, rcp45, rcp60 and rcp85). In order to calculate relative severity for the indicator of changing climatic conditions over the whole bounding box we used RF-model prediction (as proportion of votes for the focal class) as a measure of appropriate climatic conditions for the focal macrogroup, and considered the threshold for equal specificity and sensitivity as the threshold at which environmental conditions shift to favor a different macrogroup (collapse threshold, CT). We compared predictions based on current climatic condition (initial value) and predictions based on each combination of GCM and RCP for 2050 (final value). We summarized the results of the 20 combinations of GCMs and RCP to calculate the best estimate and plausible bounds (range including 90% probabilities) for the threat category (Bland et al. 2017)⁠. This indicator measures the expected decline for the next 50 years and thus corresponds to subcriterion C2a.</Data-description><Values>Model performance on current data was not good enough, and no future predictions were attempted</Values><Overall-Severity units="%" method="lower-upper"></Overall-Severity><Overall-Extent units="%" method="lower-upper"></Overall-Extent><Collapse-threshold>We considered the threshold for equal specificity and sensitivity as the threshold at which environmental conditions shift to favor a different macrogroup.</Collapse-threshold></Indicator-data></Key-indicator></Key-indicator-variable></Subcriterion><Subcriterion name="C2b"><Summaries><Summary lang="en">The data used to estimate deterioration of environmental conditions was relevant to future  time frames, but not applicable to present, historic or past time frames. Alternative data sources need to be considered for assessing this subcriterion.</Summary></Summaries><Rationale>This subcriterion was not evaluated.</Rationale><Category>NE</Category></Subcriterion><Subcriterion name="C3"><Summaries><Summary lang="en">The data used to estimate deterioration of environmental conditions was relevant to present and future  time frames, but not applicable to historic or past time frames. Alternative data sources need to be considered for assessing this subcriterion.</Summary></Summaries><Rationale>No suitable indicator was evaluated for this period of time.</Rationale><Category>NE</Category></Subcriterion></Subcriterions></Criterion><Criterion name="D"><Summaries><Summary lang="en">For criterion D we considered that large vertebrates (and specially large mammals) are a characteristic component of forests, and their due to overexploitation has an impact in important biotic associations in ecosystems (Galetti &amp; Dirzo 2013; Dirzo et al. 2014)⁠.  We used recent estimates of hunting-depletion distances to assess potential ecosystem degradation severity and extent in tropical regions (Benítez-López et al. 2017)⁠. We did not find reliable indicators of other important threatening processes like invasive species or selective logging at a continental scale, but we considered that increased human use intensity could be used as indirect indicator of those (Ellis et al. 2010).</Summary></Summaries><Rationale name="D">Subcriterion D3 was above the threshold for Vulnerable but below the threshold for Endangered, thus under this criterion this Macrogroup is considered Vulnerable</Rationale><Category><Category>VU</Category></Category><Subcriterions><Subcriterion name="D1"><Summaries><Summary lang="en">We estimate changes in resource use intensity by reclassifying the reconstructed land cover classes for 1900 and 2000 from the Anthrome products (Ellis et al. 2010). We crossed the potential distribution of the Macrogroup with the distinct woodland cover classes, and calculated the proportion of area that changed between the two Anthromes layers from low intensity ('wild woodlands' or 'used woodlands') to high intensity of use ('populated woodlands' or 'residential woodlands'). Mean relative severity was 17.3 %, and it did not reach any of the thresholds for Vulnerable.</Summary></Summaries><Rationale>Mean relative severity was 17.3 %, and it did not reach any of the thresholds for Vulnerable.</Rationale><Category>LC</Category><Key-indicator-variable name="Resource use intensity"><Key-indicator><Indicator-data><Data-source>Ellis, E.C., Goldewijk, K.K., Siebert, S., Lightman, D. &amp; Ramankutty, N. (2010). Anthropogenic transformation of the biomes, 1700 to 2000. Glob. Ecol. Biogeogr., 19, 589–606.</Data-source><Data-description>We estimate changes in resource use intensity by reclassifying the reconstructed land cover classes for 1900 and 2000 from the Anthrome products (Ellis et al. 2010). We crossed the potential distribution of the Macrogroup with the distinct woodland cover classes, and calculated the proportion of area that changed between the two Anthromes layers from low intensity ('wild woodlands' or 'used woodlands') to high intensity of use ('populated woodlands' or 'residential woodlands'). We assume that the class 'Natural woodlands' represents natural conditions and the other classes represent increasing amounts of disruption leading to collapse ('Natural' &lt; 'Used' &lt; 'Populated' &lt; 'Residential'). We considered equal step weights for changes between consecutive classes, thus a change from 'Natural' to 'Used' or from 'Used' to 'Populated' was represented as RS=25%, while a change from 'Natural' to 'Populated' or from 'Used' to 'Residential' would be represented by RS=50%, etc.</Data-description><Values><Value method="mean estimated"><Severity units="%">17.3</Severity><Extent units="%">100</Extent></Value><Value method="estimated"><Severity units="%">&gt;30</Severity><Extent units="%">69.4</Extent></Value><Value method="estimated"><Severity units="%">&gt;50</Severity><Extent units="%">0</Extent></Value><Value method="estimated"><Severity units="%">&gt;80</Severity><Extent units="%">0</Extent></Value></Values></Indicator-data><Overall-Severity units="%" method="lower-upper">30</Overall-Severity><Overall-Extent units="%" method="lower-upper">69.4</Overall-Extent><Collapse-threshold>We do not have a quantitative estimate of collapse, but assume that the class 'Natural woodlands' represents natural conditions and the other classes represent increasing amounts of disruption leading to collapse ('Natural' &lt; 'Used' &lt; 'Populated' &lt; 'Residential').</Collapse-threshold></Key-indicator></Key-indicator-variable></Subcriterion><Subcriterion name="D2a"><Summaries><Summary lang="en"/></Summaries><Rationale>No suitable indicator was evaluated for this period of time.</Rationale><Category/></Subcriterion><Subcriterion name="D2b"><Summaries><Summary lang="en"/></Summaries><Rationale/><Category>DD</Category><Key-indicator-variable name="Potential defaunation"><Key-indicator><Indicator-data><Data-source>Benítez-López, A., Alkemade, J.R.M., Schipper, A.M., Ingram, D.J., Verweij, P.A., Eikelboom, J. &amp; Huijbregts, M. (2017). The impact of hunting on tropical mammal and bird populations. Science (80-. )., 356, 180–183.</Data-source><Data-source>Digital Chart of the World: road network per country</Data-source><Data-source>Friedl, M.A., Sulla-Menashe, D., Tan, B., Schneider, A., Ramankutty, N., Sibley, A. &amp; Huang, X. (2010). MODIS Collection 5 global land cover: Algorithm refinements and characterization of new datasets, 2001-2012, Collection 5.1 IGBP Land Cover.</Data-source><Data-source>World Database on Protected Areas, IUCN and UNEP-WCMC 2016</Data-source><Data-description>We applied a simplified formula relating response ratios (RR) of the abundance of mammals in hunted and unhunted sites with three variables: distance to access points for hunters (approximated by distance in km to the  main road network, from Digital Chart of the World), distance to markets for wildlife products (approximated by the distance in km to major urban centers, calculated from urban land cover in MODIS LC, version 5.1, Friedl et al. 2010)⁠ and level of protection (approximated by the distribution of any kind of protected areas, from the World Database on Protected Areas, IUCN and UNEP-WCMC 2016). According to figures and detailed results from (Benítez-López et al. 2017)⁠⁠, we used the following formula to estimate the expected RR from raster images representing the three variables: RR = -2.370 + 0.057 access + 0.010 market + 1.270 protected . We then transformed the spatial estimate of RR to an estimate of potential decline in mammal abundance as a percentage . For negative RR values we estimated the decline as: decline = (1-exp(RR)) * 100. For zero or positive RR values we assumed zero decline. An overall weighted estimate of percentage decline was calculated over the potential distribution of each Macrogroup, using mean forest cover between 2001 and 2012 as a weighting variable. We assume that the applied formula represents the potential relative decline in mammal abundance and used a collapse threshold equivalent of 10% of the original abundance. We further assume that the formula represents a current level of threat representative a 50 year window including past, present and future.</Data-description><Values><Value method="mean estimated"><Severity units="%">NA</Severity><Extent units="%">100</Extent></Value><Value method="estimated"><Severity units="%">&gt;30</Severity><Extent units="%">NA</Extent></Value><Value method="estimated"><Severity units="%">&gt;50</Severity><Extent units="%">NA</Extent></Value><Value method="estimated"><Severity units="%">&gt;80</Severity><Extent units="%">NA</Extent></Value></Values><Overall-Severity units="%" method="lower-upper"/><Overall-Extent units="%" method="lower-upper"/><Collapse-threshold>We considered a ecosystem collapsed when the mammal abundance declined to 10% of the original abundance.</Collapse-threshold></Indicator-data></Key-indicator></Key-indicator-variable></Subcriterion><Subcriterion name="D3"><Summaries><Summary lang="en">We estimate changes in resource use intensity by reclassifying the reconstructed land cover classes for 1700 and 2000 from the Anthrome products (Ellis et al. 2010). We crossed the potential distribution of the Macrogroup with the distinct woodland cover classes, and calculated the proportion of area that changed between the two Anthromes layers from low intensity ('wild woodlands' or 'used woodlands') to high intensity of use ('populated woodlands' or 'residential woodlands'). Mean relative severity was 56.2. 82.5 % of the extent had a relative severity of 50 % or higher, exceeding the threshold for Vulnerable.</Summary></Summaries><Rationale>Mean relative severity was 56.2. 82.5 % of the extent had a relative severity of 50 % or higher, exceeding the threshold for Vulnerable.</Rationale><Category>VU</Category><Key-indicator-variable name="Resource use intensity"><Key-indicator><Indicator-data><Data-source>Ellis, E.C., Goldewijk, K.K., Siebert, S., Lightman, D. &amp; Ramankutty, N. (2010). Anthropogenic transformation of the biomes, 1700 to 2000. Glob. Ecol. Biogeogr., 19, 589–606.</Data-source><Data-description>We estimate changes in resource use intensity by reclassifying the reconstructed land cover classes for 1700 and 2000 from the Anthrome products (Ellis et al. 2010). We crossed the potential distribution of the Macrogroup with the distinct woodland cover classes, and calculated the proportion of area that changed between the two Anthromes layers from low intensity ('wild woodlands' or 'used woodlands') to high intensity of use ('populated woodlands' or 'residential woodlands'). We assume that the class 'Natural woodlands' represents natural conditions and the other classes represent increasing amounts of disruption leading to collapse ('Natural' &lt; 'Used' &lt; 'Populated' &lt; 'Residential'). We considered equal step weights for changes between consecutive classes, thus a change from 'Natural' to 'Used' or from 'Used' to 'Populated' was represented as RS=25%, while a change from 'Natural' to 'Populated' or from 'Used' to 'Residential' would be represented by RS=50%, etc.</Data-description><Values><Value method="mean estimated"><Severity units="%">56.2</Severity><Extent units="%">100</Extent></Value><Value method="estimated"><Severity units="%">&gt;50</Severity><Extent units="%">82.5</Extent></Value><Value method="estimated"><Severity units="%">&gt;70</Severity><Extent units="%">48.4</Extent></Value><Value method="estimated"><Severity units="%">&gt;90</Severity><Extent units="%">0</Extent></Value></Values></Indicator-data><Overall-Severity units="%" method="lower-upper">30</Overall-Severity><Overall-Extent units="%" method="lower-upper">82.5</Overall-Extent><Collapse-threshold>We do not have a quantitative estimate of collapse, but assume that the class 'Natural woodlands' represents natural conditions and the other classes represent increasing amounts of disruption leading to collapse ('Natural' &lt; 'Used' &lt; 'Populated' &lt; 'Residential').</Collapse-threshold></Key-indicator></Key-indicator-variable></Subcriterion></Subcriterions></Criterion><Criterion name="E"><Summaries><Summary lang="en">No quantitative assessment of ecosystem collapse was performed for this assessment unit.</Summary></Summaries><Rationale name="E">This criterion was not evaluated.</Rationale><Category>NE</Category></Criterion></Criterions></Assessment-unit></Assessment-units></Ecosystem-Risk-Assessment><Content-Curations><content-curation date="2019-09-30" reviewer="Rsaurio" status="auto-generated-test"><edit-description>XML document generation through R-scripts</edit-description></content-curation></Content-Curations></Case-Study></Case-Studies>